<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true discourse of the discouerie of the plot of Monsieur du Terrail, and his confederates for the surprising of Geneua And of their apprehension, confessions, and executions done in the same, the 19. of April. 1609.</title>
            <title>Veritable discours de la descouverte de l'enterprise de Loys de Comboursier, sieur de Terrail. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20999</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7371</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100003</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99835860</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99835860</idno>
            <idno type="VID">87</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20999)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 87)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 956:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true discourse of the discouerie of the plot of Monsieur du Terrail, and his confederates for the surprising of Geneua And of their apprehension, confessions, and executions done in the same, the 19. of April. 1609.</title>
                  <title>Veritable discours de la descouverte de l'enterprise de Loys de Comboursier, sieur de Terrail. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by John Windet] for R. Bonian and H. Walley, and are to be sold at the signe of the Spread-Eagle, right ouer against the great north-doore of S. Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Veritable discours de la descouverte de l'enterprise de Loys de Comboursier, sieur de Terrail.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Combourcier, Louis de, d. 1609.</term>
               <term>Geneva (Republic) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:87:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:87:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TRVE DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COVRSE OF THE DISCOVERIE OF THE Plot of Monſieur du TERRAIL, and his Confederates for the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing of <hi>Geneua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND OF THEIR APPREHENSION, CONFESSIONS, AND EXECVTIONS done in the ſame, The 19. of <hi>April.</hi> 1609.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>R. Bonian</hi> and <hi>H. Walley,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Signe of the Spread-Eagle, right ouer againſt the great North-doore of S. <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1609.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:87:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:87:2"/>
            <head>A TRVE DISCOVRSE Of the Plot of Monſieur du TERRAIL, againſt <hi>Geneua,</hi> the 19. of April, 1609.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now about three yeeres ſince, aduice was giuen from ſome of good place, that <hi>Monſier du Terrail</hi> being much diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, that he was not ſeconded in his vndertakings in the Low-countreys, whereby he foreſaw that in the end all would be loſt, had reſolued to ſerue the Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> and alſo had openly giuen out, that hee had in his Forge a notable enterpriſe vpon <hi>Geneua.</hi> In purſute of which, he was ſeene ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to come to <hi>Paris,</hi> with pretence of reconciling himſelfe to the Kings fauour. But good aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was giuen, that hee was to come for <hi>Sauoy.</hi> Theſe his diſsignes were then interrupted by a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, hee committed in the <hi>Louure</hi> in preſence of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:87:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> King. Whereupon to flie the great diſpleaſure of the King, he ſoone turn'd head to the <hi>Archdukes,</hi> from whence after ſome ſixe Moneths ſtay, he vndertooke a Pilgrimage to our Lady of <hi>Loretto,</hi> with one <hi>Baſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de</hi> an Inginer, whom hee tooke to him for Counſell and aide of his executions: They went a foote, and in their returne had priuate conference with the D. of <hi>Sauoy.</hi> Notwithſtanding, the Count <hi>Fuentes</hi> adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this <hi>Terrail</hi> otherwiſe, giuing him to vnderſtand that the Duke would embrace his Seruice againſt <hi>Geneua,</hi> but it would bee his ouerthrow. The Duke communicated to him and his man his diſſignes for <hi>Geneua,</hi> as ſhall followingly appeare by Letters, and Confeſſions; and from that time they reſted in <hi>Sauoy,</hi> making two Voyages to <hi>Turin</hi> for the ſame affaire. They of <hi>Geneua</hi> had preſently great diſtruſt, receiuing aduertiſements one in the necke of another, from all parts, of a notable, and in a maner vnauoidable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe againſt them, carried by <hi>Monſieur du Terrail.</hi> All the Gouernours either of Prouinces or Places adioyning from the <hi>French</hi> King, gaue diuers very pregnant intelligences, but without any way diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering the meanes.</p>
            <p>The Sauoyards, already ſang the Triumph, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to be inſerted in an Almanacke of one of their Aſtrologers, the certaintie of the Act about the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of May (which was the time deſtined to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution) in the end of his predictions. Which Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manacke Printed at <hi>Lions,</hi> was in exceeding requeſt for this particularitie. The <hi>French</hi> King alſo aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed the State of <hi>Geneua,</hi> that they ſhould doe him a good ſeruice, if they could ſeiſe him, and gaue them
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:87:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> this meanes, aſſuring them that he was about <hi>Geneua,</hi> or the Countrey of <hi>Berne,</hi> and if they could diſpacth him, the Act would be to him moſt acceptable.</p>
            <p>While they were in this doubtfull miſt, God ſent them a ſmall light, was greater then all, which ſince ſerued them as a Keye to open to the depth of the Plot, and to conuince firſt the ſeruant of <hi>Terrail,</hi> and afterward himſelfe. <hi>Terrail,</hi> hauing on a day plaide at Tenniſe at <hi>Chamberi,</hi> and retiring in his heate to rubbe and refreſh himſelfe, went into a bed; where, while a ſeruant of the Tenniſe Court warmed him a ſhirt, there came into him <hi>Baſtide,</hi> and ſome other, well marked by this youth, and preſented him a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which was the Plot of <hi>Geneua,</hi> and diſcourſt ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly among themſelues, as of ſome matter of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: Inſomuch as the fellow ouer hearing them, name ſome places of the Fortreſſe of <hi>Geneua,</hi> leant his eare with more attention; and gathered for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that their diſcourſe was about ſome Enterpriſe, they had againſt that place; and heard that <hi>Terrail</hi> after long conference, made no difficultie ſaue of the meanes to raiſe ſufficient Force to carrie the affaire. In which point being ſatisfied by the aſſiſtants, hee brake out alowde in theſe tearmes. They are ours, they cannot eſcape vs. Which words being well marked by the youth of the Tenniſe Court, who had a Brother in the Garriſon of <hi>Geneua,</hi> and whome he was willing to ſaue from this miſchiefe, he went pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently and diſcouered it to a Towneſman of <hi>Geneua,</hi> who was then in <hi>Chamberi</hi> about ſome buſineſſe. This Townſman made faithfull report thereof to the Magiſtrate of <hi>Geneua,</hi> and the brother of the youth.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:87:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>After this time, they of <hi>Geneua</hi> vſed all deligence by ſpies, to know his comming and going, and had him followed whereſoeuer he went. In the end they had certaine notice of his paſſing the Mountaines ſome ſixe or ſeuen weekes before, and that hee was come backe by the way of the Lake <hi>Leman,</hi> wherup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they gaue preſent aduertiſement to all the Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffes of the Countrey vnder the Lord of <hi>Berne.</hi> With the particular notes, and markes of the perſon of the ſaid <hi>Terrail;</hi> praying them to haue an eye on him, and poſſeſſe themſelues of his perſon, in caſe he paſſe by their Territories: for which the Magiſtrates of <hi>Berne</hi> being ſo aſſured of the practiſes of the Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> againſt thoſe of <hi>Geneua</hi> their confederates and againſt themſelues alſo, gaue expreſſe commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. To this came a remarkeable accident; a Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con of <hi>Iuerdun,</hi> a Towne of the <hi>Bernoys</hi> neare the frontire of the county of <hi>Burgoigne,</hi> being at <hi>Geneua</hi> came to ſalute the chiefe <hi>Syndicke</hi> of the Towne, and brought him Letters; He, after other diſcourſe, told him of the manifold aduertiſement they had, of the enemies diſſeignes againſt <hi>Geneua,</hi> and the country of <hi>Berne,</hi> but eſpecially the Towne of <hi>Iuerdun,</hi> a place of greateſt importance, being the key of the whole country, ſtrong by ſcituation, though ill fortified, and bounding vtmoſt on <hi>Burgoigne;</hi> He gaue him alſo the marks of <hi>Terrail,</hi> of whom they had got a Picture at <hi>Geneua,</hi> becauſe he was to come in Perſon to take a view of the Towne. It hapned certaine dayes after, that <hi>Terrail</hi> returning from <hi>Turin</hi> paſſed the Lake, and arriued in the Country of <hi>Berne,</hi> but not at the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:87:4"/> known and ordinary port, went through the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and viſiting the places of moſt importance, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer lodging in Townes or knowne places, but vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages &amp; peaſants houſes til he came to <hi>Iuerdun:</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtaide he there, but hauing ſome day left, paſſed on further. Paſſing ouer the Bridge of the Towne he met the Bayliffe with others, whom hee ſaluted, but they obſerued him not. Being paſt the Bridge, making ſhew of ſtay for ſome other cauſe, hee turned backe toward <hi>Iuerdun,</hi> taking a diligent view of the Scite, defences, and ſtate thereof, which was noted by them that were yet vpon the bridge, who thought hee did it onely for the marke of his way in trauell. But as he was gone a little further, the foreſaid Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con (being in a Garden) eſpied him comming a farre of: and obſeruing his countenance began to ſuſpect it might be <hi>Terrail;</hi> and to aſſure himſelfe better, knowing that he was bald, made him a low congee to draw him to the putting of his hat, which he did; and the Deacon being now confirmed, ran preſently to the Bayliffe, telling him what he thought.</p>
            <p>All they which were by, hauing marked the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of <hi>Terrail,</hi> how he returned, and tooke ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uay of the place, wiſhed the Bailife to ſend after him. He immediatly diſpatched two, and gaue them in charge to obſerue which way he tooke. If hee went from <hi>Burgoigne,</hi> they ſhould returne without farther purſuite; If toward, they ſhould follow him to his lodging, without making any ſhew to know him, but onely to be confirmed in the markes of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. There happened alſo, (as is aſſured for truth)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:87:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> another notable act, ſigne or argument of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence. <hi>Terrail</hi> hauing paſt the village of <hi>Villeboeuf,</hi> which is not aboue halfe a league from the way of <hi>Burgoigne,</hi> to lodge in the ſaid county that night, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ouer a ſlough, his horſe ſtucke, ſo that hee was faine to turne backe, and goe ouer a planke, vpon which his horſe ſtumbling, ſo that hee halted, hee was faine to reſolue of lodging that night in <hi>Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boeuf.</hi> Hee had no guide with him, that knew the Country, which was a great cauſe of his ſurpriſe; For a Guide might eaſily haue ſet him in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try betweene <hi>Berne,</hi> and <hi>Friburge,</hi> which in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces was not aboue two Harguebuſſe ſhot from him, and there he had beene in fafety, through the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixture of their iuriſdiction. But at <hi>Friburg,</hi> hee had found all fauour, where his enterpriſes, had made them houer for aduantage againſt the <hi>Bernoys,</hi> vpon the great difference, which they haue had long for their land poſſeſt in common, and which the <hi>Fribur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> would deuide to the detriment of thoſe of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed religion, which is onely exerciſed in almoſt al thoſe places. After his taking he was very ſory, and more when he knew how eaſily he might haue been ſaued by this meanes. Being come to the foreſaide Village of <hi>Villeboeuf,</hi> the two that were ſent from <hi>Iuerdun,</hi> hauing houſ'd him carefully, one of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned with all ſpeede to the Bayliffe, to giue him the notice, who ſent preſently foure horſ-men, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducted by the Captaine of the Caſtell of <hi>Iuerdun,</hi> to force him backe to the Bayliffe, and bad them ſtrengthen themſelues with the force of the Country. They at
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:87:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> their arriuall in the morning found <hi>Monſieur du Terrail</hi> booted, and ready to take horſe; to whom the Hoſt, and other aduertiſed of the buſines, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that he could not paſſe the Mountaines, for two great <hi>Corps du guard,</hi> that would let no man goe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till hee had giuen accompt of his Voyage to the Bayliffe of <hi>Iuerdun.</hi> This was ſtrengthened by the Horſe that came that morning, at which <hi>Baſtide</hi> began to ſhew a curſing diſlike of the action, <hi>Terrail</hi> diſpoſed of himſelfe very peaceably, to returne to <hi>Iuerdun</hi> with theſe fiue or ſixe Horſemen, whom with his people he might eaſily haue ſlaine, or made to quit him by flight, if he had foreſeene his calamity. After his taking he repented himſelfe much, that hee had not ſhowne his great courage at this inſtant. But God blinded him, neither ſince hath beene noted in him any ſparke of valour, and dexterity, whereby he might haue ſaued himſelfe diuers times, as ſhall appeare in the ſequell; Being returned to <hi>Iuerdun,</hi> and demaunded by the Bayliffe (a ſubtle and experienced man) what hee was? He ſaid hee was a Gentleman of <hi>Dauphine,</hi> and cald <hi>Paule de Conſtans,</hi> and going to <hi>Lorraine</hi> to follow a ſute, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd him nearely, and therefore deſir'd the Bayliffe for preſent diſpatch: which anſwers ſo ſlightly grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, made the Bayliffe more ſuſpitious, ſo that hee reſolued to ſeiſe him till hee were better informed, and demanded his ſword, which he rendred him wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and was lodged in an Inne in <hi>Iuerdun,</hi> with a guard ſet vpon him of foure Men, day and night. Among other cauſes of ſuſpition, being at <hi>Villeboeuf,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:87:6"/> and ſeeing that he muſt returne, hauing no meanes to eſcape, his people being taken by the multitude, he called for a Candle, with which he burnt a long Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter writ of all ſides; This being ſeene and demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded what it was, he aſſured them that it was a Letter writ to <hi>Madam de Criqui</hi> his Kinſwoman, to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede for him to the King, and hath euer ſince to his end maintained it, and that he burnt it, leaſt his name and quality ſhould be knowne. The Bayliffe to aſſure himſelfe, ſent preſently to <hi>Geneua,</hi> to haue ſome that knew <hi>Terrail.</hi> They immediatly ſent one of the chiefe of the Towne, and a Souldier borne in <hi>Geneua,</hi> who had ſerued vnder <hi>Terrail</hi> in the Low Countries, &amp; had giuen diuers aduiſes of this enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, which he had heard from <hi>Terrails</hi> owne mouth and ſundry of his followers.</p>
            <p>When theſe two arriued at <hi>Iuerdun,</hi> it was thought good, that the Souldier ſhould come in vpon the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, where <hi>Terrail</hi> was at Supper; which hee did, and ſate downe rudely; making no ſhew to ſee him, <hi>Terrail</hi> ſeeing him, was much troubled and changed colour, as if his heart failed him, fayning hee was not well, and required to haue his bed warmed, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew (being much out of temper) with his ordinary Guard to his Chamber, whither he cauſed the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier to be called, and entertained him with very cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous diſcourſe, to enduce him to confeſſe, if he were not ſent thither to diſcouer him: which the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er affirming, he began to talke ſtrangely to him: That he knew not what they of <hi>Geneua</hi> had to doe with him? that he had had diuers aduertiſements in <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:87:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> that they laid wait for him at <hi>Geneua,</hi> &amp; that they would make vſe of this ſouldier to diſcouer him: that he would die a braue Knight as he was, &amp; innocent. That he had neuer had to doe with them of <hi>Sauoy.</hi> Then he began to practiſe with the ſouldier to helpe him to ſcape promiſing him 1000. crownes, <hi>Baſtide</hi> offred him preſently 100. crowns down, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed. <hi>Terraill</hi> prayd him to come, &amp; viſite him eare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the morning: for hee had ſome great thing to tell him. In the meane time the Bailiffe aduertiſed of the truth, and finding it not good hee ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe any longer with the ſouldier, ſent to haue him brought to the Caſtle with his ſeruant, where they were ſeuerally lodged, and well guarded. After they knew at <hi>Geneua</hi> of his taking, they purpoſed to ſend to demaund him of the Lords of <hi>Berne,</hi> iudging that in their hands, they ſhould hardly draw the trueth of the enterpriſe from him, and that mighty inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions, and other meanes might eaſily ſaue him. They ſent therefore to <hi>Berne,</hi> one of the Syndicks of <hi>Geneua,</hi> who being firſt heard by the Councell of 25. at <hi>Berne,</hi> hee ſhowed them the great and iuſt grounds, that they of <hi>Geneua</hi> had to deſire, to haue <hi>Terrail</hi> in their hands, that they had proofes and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties of his practiſes, that the witneſſes which they had at <hi>Geneua</hi> could not without danger bee ſent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, that it was the common cauſe of both the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagued States, that the enterpriſes threatned an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable blow, that thoſe of <hi>Geneua</hi> in the like caſes had deliuerd priſoners to the Seigniory of <hi>Berne,</hi> that very lately the Kings Gariſon had accorded a priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:87:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> enterpriſing the like action, and that it would be of great conſequence to diuert all enterpriſers, if they ſaw, they could not with ſafety come about <hi>Geneua,</hi> nor the territories of the King, or their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips of <hi>Berne.</hi> In the end the leſſer Councell of <hi>Berne,</hi> finding themſelues much perplexed, aſſembled the great Councell of 200. and the ſame things beeing propoſed to them, it was with great clemencie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by generall aſſent, that <hi>Terrail</hi> ſhould bee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen into the hands of them of <hi>Geneua</hi> with his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant.</p>
            <p>The Ambaſſador of the King, reſident at <hi>Solurre,</hi> much approoued this reſolution, fearing that hee could not bee enough aſſured in the hands of thoſe of <hi>Berne.</hi> The newes of this grant being arriued at <hi>Geneua,</hi> they vſed the extreameſt diligence and dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritie, to perſwade the Brother of the ſeruant of the Tenniſe-court keeper of <hi>Chamberi</hi> aboue named, to goe to <hi>Chamberi</hi> and winne his brother to come with faire promiſes, and pretexts, which hee execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted faithfully and readily; ſo that within three dayes he was at <hi>Geneua,</hi> and ſerued infinitely to the Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie. They alſo ſudenly ſent the Souldier which had knowen <hi>Terrail</hi> to <hi>Monlori</hi> hard by <hi>Lyons,</hi> where they knew there was a Souldier, who had bene ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, <hi>Terrail</hi> his Horſe-keeper, and had heard the diſcourſe touching the Enterpriſe of <hi>Geneua,</hi> and had oftentimes told it <hi>Beleine.</hi> (So was the name of the Souldier of <hi>Geneua.</hi>) But the Horſe-keeper was not there, yet at <hi>Lyons</hi> the foreſaid <hi>Baleine</hi> found a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier his <hi>Camerado,</hi> who aſſured him, that at diuers
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:87:7"/> times the ſaid Horſe-keeper had told him all his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, whereof <hi>Baleine</hi> tooke an ample and expreſſe Copie by the hand of a publike Notarie. Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur du <hi>Terrail</hi> was deliuered to the Syndicke of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua,</hi> and conducted by a ſtrong Gard of <hi>Iuerdun</hi> to <hi>Morges,</hi> a little Towne ſcituate vpon the Lake <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> eight Leagues from <hi>Geneua,</hi> and there was put to the Gard of the Bailiffe of <hi>Morges,</hi> till hee ſhould be ſent for to <hi>Geneua</hi> by water, which ſtay of him was made by the two hundred, till they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a publike Acte vnder the Seale of <hi>Geneua,</hi> that this was done without conſequence, or preiudice of their iuriſdiction, of their proper grace and curteſie to their confederates.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Terrail</hi> was caried alone from <hi>Iuerdum,</hi> his Serui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour was left there, for feare they ſhould Parlee, and practiſe together. By the way hee entertained the Syndicke with diuers deſperate diſcourſes; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from time to time, what Death will you put me to at <hi>Geneua?</hi> He ſhewed that hee was much afraid, they would deliuer him to the King; and for that had changd his Name and faſhion; and that his feare was the King hauing him would keep him in the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile. That if he were farre from him, he could make his peace to his great aduantage &amp; libertie, but now he muſt ſtand at the deuotion of the King: Yet ſince, he hath affirmed, that his greateſt deſire was, hee might not fall into the hands of thoſe of <hi>Geneua</hi> but might be ſent to the King, hoping by his great Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance eaſily to make his peace. And ſince his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming hither hath vſed greater cunning, giuing out
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:87:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> that he diſſwaded the Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> in the Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe of <hi>Geneua,</hi> but with ſo friuolous reaſons that we eaſily knew, they were Diſcourſes built but to deceiue. He lulled the Bayliffe of <hi>Morges</hi> ſo aſleepe with faire words and promiſes, that they with Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neur <hi>D'eſdiguieres</hi> ſent to intercede for him to <hi>Berne,</hi> had free paſſage thorough <hi>Morges;</hi> and the Bailiffe of <hi>Morges</hi> refuſed to yeeld him to them, which ſhould next Morning haue caried him by water to <hi>Geneua,</hi> and gaue <hi>Terrail</hi> good meanes to ſaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, if God had not left him deſtitute of his great courage and ſpirit. Hee had there alſo a very ſlender Gard, libertie to walke about all the Caſtle, meanes of Conference with whom hee would, and to write to his friends.</p>
            <p>Hee got the fauour of the people there, by his good behauiour, iuſtification, and bountie: So that if but twentie reſolute men had preſented them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, he might haue bene reſcued, and the eaſier, in reſpect the Paſſage ouer, was but three ſmall French Leagues; and the other Bank was wholly the Dukes. Nay, if he had had aduertiſement but to come out of the Caſtle, he had beene ſafe by them of <hi>Morges,</hi> they were ſo much at his deuotion.</p>
            <p>They of <hi>Geneua</hi> ſent preſently to <hi>Berne</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, and re-enforce their requeſt to haue him, which was confirmed with great indignation, and threatnings againſt the Bailiffe of <hi>Morges.</hi> The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of <hi>Monſier D'eſdiguieres,</hi> was very faint, and conditionall, as that if hee had not enterpriſed any thing againſt the King, or the Lords of <hi>Berne,</hi> or <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuâ:</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:87:8"/> which made thoſe of <hi>Berne</hi> the leſſe hearkning. The Bailiffe of <hi>Morges</hi> before the anſwere to thoſe of <hi>Geneua,</hi> receiued peremptory commaund to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Terrail</hi> preſently, which he was conſtrained to doe. Since, the Bailiffe was ſeuerely cited by a day to appeare in perſon at <hi>Berne;</hi> and it is held, that he is put already from his charge, and ſhal be from his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, there being many preſumptions, and ſome confeſſions of <hi>Terrail,</hi> that he was promiſed tenne thouſand Crownes, if he ſo wrought, that hee might not be carried to <hi>Geneua,</hi> or at leaſt that his man might not come there: which the foreſaid Bailiffe had promiſed him, hoping by the meanes of his great credite, and kindred to make it good. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts Cantons and the kindred of <hi>Terrail</hi> trauelled earneſtly at <hi>Berne</hi> to ſaue him. Some of them ariued too late. The Lords of <hi>Berne</hi> haue carried them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues very affectionately and zealouſly, in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, moued thereto chiefly by the braues of thoſe of <hi>Friburge,</hi> who with the wind of this enterpriſe had blowne vp their valours, but ſince are become ſlacke and ſupple. <hi>Terrail</hi> was caried by water in a Frigate, armed, and by the way, one of the Seigniors of the citie which accompanied him, made him very gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and honorable offer; that if he would declare what might appertaine to the preſent aſſurance of their citie, he would promiſe him in the name of the Seigniorie, pardon, libertie, courteous vſage, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for him to the King. But he ſtill denied all, though much troubled, and perplexed; ſaying, that he was no man to be tortured, that they ought not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:87:9"/> to offer him the racke; that he ſhould then ſpeake as well what was not; as what was. Being ariued at <hi>Geneua,</hi> the fourteenth of April, about midnight, they lodgd him in the Towne houſe well guarded. The next morning being ſent for to the Councell, they againe beſpake him very honorably, &amp; opened vnto him, the power which they had to ſaue him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer him to France; that hee ſhould quit them of the paines of producing ſuch things, as they had in their hands to conuince him, and ſhould be aiding to himſelfe; promiſing him all courteous entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, freedom, and mediation to the King. This was repeated more then ſixe times. But ſtil he perſiſted to denie with great execrations, renouncing his part in Paradiſe, &amp; in ſuch manner, &amp;c. So that in the end, it was told him, ſince hee would not bee good to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, there was no more grace for him: and after that, made him anſwere as a <hi>Criminall,</hi> ſpeaking to him rough, and harſhly, which much amated him. Being confronted with the ſouldier <hi>La Baleine,</hi> hee denied all euen to the leaſt things, and where al apparance made againſt him. Three dayes after his arriuall, His man was brought to <hi>Geneua,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently led to the priſon: whether <hi>Terrail</hi> was alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy remoued; In the morning the 15. of Aprill, <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtide</hi> was ſhowne to the yong fellow of the Tennis Court of <hi>Chamberi,</hi> from whom came the ſureſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence: who marking with good view his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, pronounced aſſuredly, that this was he that preſented the foreſayd paper to <hi>Terrail:</hi> and had held with him the diſcourſe aboue mentioned: The
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:87:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> yong man being asked apart what apparell <hi>Baſtide</hi> had then on, told them, and <hi>Baſtide</hi> confeſſed it to be true, but denied the fact of the paper, or any ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, as alſo did <hi>Terrail.</hi> In the end, they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the yong man conſtant to what he had ſaid; it was reſolued, that <hi>Baſtide</hi> ſhould be put to the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which was done. He bare two great ierkes of the ſtrappado, at the third he confeſt all. This reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of putting <hi>Baſtide</hi> to the torture, was alſo founded vpon this reaſon. A Citizen of <hi>Geneua</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing by chance ſeene <hi>Baſtide</hi> in the priſon yard, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that he had ſupped one night with the ſaid <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtide</hi> in a village hard by, and that in the morning the hoſte of the place told him, that this <hi>Baſtide</hi> had drawne ſeuerall cards and plots of Fortification, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his departure; whereby he was knowen by the hoſte for an Enginer: of which being then asked, he confeſſed it, and yet afterward in priſon denied all ſtiffely. But now hauing confeſſed all, he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted with <hi>Terrail,</hi> who began to diſcouer it. But <hi>Baſtide</hi> perſeuered in his affirmation, and <hi>Terrail</hi> was preſented to the torture, wher, with teares in his eies, he confeſſed the whole fact voluntarily, and receiued no touch. His confeſſions concerned <hi>Geneua, Berne,</hi> the French King, and the States of the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; but thoſe concerning <hi>Berne</hi> and <hi>Geneua,</hi> were onely made publike: The King and the States were preſently aduertiſed of that concerned them. Firſt, the ſaid <hi>Baſtide</hi> confeſſed that he was an Enginer, and had long ſerued the Archduke; ſince, hee had giuen himſelfe to <hi>Terrail,</hi> to execute his vndertaking. Hee
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:87:10"/> had bin bred a Scholler, a braue fellow of his perſon, very ſubtill, and experienced in matter of fortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a cunning viewer of their weakeneſſes. He returned from his pilgrimage about foure or fiue mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neths ſince, with his maſter. Paſſing by <hi>Turin,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Sauoy</hi> had conference with them both about the towne of <hi>Geneua,</hi> to the ſurpriſe whereof they offered him their ſeruice, and for the following of this deſigne reſolued to viſite, and take view of the gates, the guardes, the water port, and whole ſtate of the towne: whereupon <hi>Baſtide</hi> vndertooke the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the towne, and hauing viewed it all; repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the whole Plot of the Town, what was reformed in the fortification ſince the laſt <hi>Eſcalada:</hi> Following which, <hi>Terrails</hi> old Plot was altered; nor could <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rail</hi> &amp; <hi>Baſtide</hi> agree on the meanes of the Enterpriſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Terrail</hi> inclining to the ſurpriſe of ſome port by <hi>Petard,</hi> or otherwiſe. <hi>Baſtide</hi> vrged againe, that it was a matter of infinite hazard, for the great number of defences which are at the Gates, and the dilligence which they vſe, and after ſome conteſt, the deuiſe of <hi>Baſtide,</hi> was approued to take the way of the water port, which was not ſo well Guarded, and which being poſſeſt by a competent number, they might eaſily come vp to the hart of the Towne, without daunger, and the Entrie well executed, <hi>Baſtide</hi> made no difficulty in the carying of the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, being an eaſie thing to Seaſe on the water port, by reaſon of the neareneſſe, and he did aduiſe to caſt themſelues into certaine narrow Lanes vnchay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and couered ouer, which hereafter the Towne hath purpoſed to cloſe vp for preuention of the like.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:87:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Terrail</hi> hauing heard all, yeelded himſelfe to this aduiſe; and parted with <hi>Baſtide,</hi> to paſſe himſelfe ouer, to the other ſide of the Lake aboue at <hi>Euian,</hi> and ſtaid there eight daies; informing himſelfe particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of all the water men, which vſed to <hi>Geneua</hi> in great numbers, about the diſpoſition, the Guides, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences of the water port, their ſearching of Boates, and other things pertaining to the Nauigation of the Lake, and learned many defaults in the Guard, and to be more aſſured ſent <hi>Baſtide</hi> to <hi>Morges</hi> to the end, that taking paſſage in one of the <hi>Barques</hi> of <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua,</hi> that on certaine daies goe thether to Market, hee might without ſuſpicion at their returne obſerue the whole ſtate of the water port, and the landing place: which he ſo readily, and ably executed, that no man ſuſpected him. Such a like ſpie was taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two yeares ago, who had groſſely tooke a view of the chaines; and being skared, and taken faltering in his anſwers, confeſſed (by Torture) that hee was ſent to view the place, without knowing any other thing belonging to the enterpriſe, or ſo much as the man that ſent him: for which he was taken to be one of <hi>Terrails</hi> party, and was hanged: ſince they haue re-enforced the port, with a ranke of double chaines, fifty paces from the firſt, but this would not ſerue to warrant againſt an enterpriſe like that of <hi>Sluce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Terrail</hi> then, and <hi>Baſtide,</hi> who returned to him by Land, hauing a new, viewed the water port by which he paſt, aſſured themſelues of the certainty and facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the buſineſſe, and tooke vpon them, that they two would be the chiefe and leaders in the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Proiect was this, <hi>Geneua</hi> hath on the <hi>North</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:87:11"/> ſide the Lake <hi>Leman</hi> which ſtretcheth it ſelfe in length at leaſt fifty French Leagues; on the Weſt ſide the Country of <hi>Berne;</hi> on the Eaſt ſide that of <hi>Sauoy;</hi> In the height of which there are great Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, where growes great ſtore of Wood, which the watermen of <hi>Geneua</hi> vſually bring home for fuell to their Towne, in great Flat Boates, and chiefely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend this worke about the Moneth of May, in great troupes, the Wood being then dry which was felled the <hi>Autumne</hi> before. The deſigne of <hi>Terrail</hi> was to Seaſe foure or fiue of theſe great Boates, and to lodge couertly vnder the wood piled for the nonce, in each Boate, a hundred, or two hundred of thoſe men, which might come in without any ſuſpicion, the counterfait watermen, being clothed in the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite of ours: As for the ſearch ſhuld be made at their entry, they cared not for it, being determined to leap out all at once, and kill. For the Muſter of thoſe troopes it ſhould be in the Valleyes of thoſe Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, remoued from the commerce of the people of <hi>Geneua,</hi> &amp; at the appointed time charge thoſe Boates, with the riſing and fauor of the Moone, which vſeth to ſhine certaine dayes of that Moneth. <hi>Terrail</hi> was appointed to be in the firſt Boate, after the firſt onſet was giuen, other troopes ſhould bee ready of Knights and Gentlemen, which they might eaſily raiſe, vnder the pretext of the Mariage of <hi>Mounſieur Denemours,</hi> which was to be celebrated at <hi>Aneci</hi> in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoy,</hi> ſixe Leagues from <hi>Geneua,</hi> and though the defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and ſtoppe of this Mariage might cauſe ſome difficulty, yet they had ſuch good incountry and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie elſewhere, that they held the Action for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>infallible.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:87:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> The eaſineſſe was this, that they might imbarque ſecretly hauing the winde fauourable to cary them in a quarter of the time, that was required by Land, the ſearch was vſed to be made very negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, and within the Towne they had nothing to care for, the ſaid ſearch being made a good while after the Boates were arriued, fiue hundred men or more brought ſodainely into the Towne, might eaſily giue worke to all the people, if they were poſſeſt but of a Canon at a Gate, and the water port, by which the Land-forces might enter in groſſe and a flote. It was alſo deſigned in a ſeaſon, when the Towne was vnfurniſhed of men by reaſon of the Hay harueſt, and other buſineſſe of the field, and in a time of the day very fitting, to wit, when they were all at Dinner, and the Towne very ſolitary. They haue alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed ſince their condemnation, that their voyage through the Country of <hi>Berne,</hi> was to Spy the Country, to purſue their victory after their ſurpriſe of <hi>Geneua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Terrail</hi> went into the Low-Counrries to take his leaue of the Arch-duke, and bring away the reſt of his goods, which he had there, and draw along with him a number of the beſt executioners, and watermen that he could get.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Terrail</hi> and <hi>Baſtide</hi> agreed, eſpecially in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, whereby it appeared that the chiefe ground of their enterpriſe proceeded from them; againſt which they haue ſince giuen very good preuentions for our ſafty hereafter, and alſo <hi>Terrail</hi> drew, on a paper with his owne hand, a deuiſe to warrant any Gates againſt a Petard.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:87:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Terrail</hi> requeſted that they would keepe him aliue betweene foure Walls, and that they would not caſt away the Soule of <hi>Baſtide</hi> by an extraordinary death. <hi>Baſtide</hi> diſpoſed himſelfe to death with an incredible magnanimity, hauing very Chriſtianly quitted all ſuperſtition, and liuely embracing whatſoeuer was propounded to him of the pure Doctrine of the Goſpell. <hi>Terrail</hi> was condemned to bee beheaded, which was executed the ninth of Aprill, <hi>Baſtide</hi> to be hanged, which was done on the Friday following being the 21. both executions were done within the City, in the place of <hi>Molard. Terrail</hi> dyed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtoutly, without changing any whit his colour or countenance, and without any geſture vnworthy his life paſt; he deſired that he might haue had his hands free: but the cuſtome and feare of his courage denyed it, and gayned him great pitty. Hee ſhewed before his execution great piety, little mingled with ſuperſtition, the apprehenſion of which things hee put off, by the holy exhortations the Miniſters made him, which he receiued with a peaceable and gentle Spirit, thanking God, who had giuen him time at his death to be conuerted to him, and meanes to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine pardon for his faultes; in cogitation of which he ſpent many teares, ſighes, and prayers, diſpiſing the reſt, as death, the ſhame of his puniſhment, and the world, while they propoſed to him comfort with all grauity, honour and comiſeration poſſible, his teares made the ſtanders by weepe, and forget all ſiniſter deſire of reuenge, Hee made his will, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed twenty Crownes to the poore of <hi>Geneua.</hi> The day before his execution they receiued Letters
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:87:12"/> from his mother adreſt to him, in which ſhee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted him, and aſſured him of the meanes they made for him in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> ſpeaking ſtill of his innocencie. <hi>Baſtide</hi> edified more by his death, yet was exceeding ſorie, that Torture had made him <hi>Terrails</hi> accuſer, of whoſe death hee knew and wiſhed hee had beene rather torne to pieces by foure Horſes. There was no interceſſion made for <hi>Terrail</hi> in <hi>Geneua,</hi> but by <hi>D'eſdiguieres,</hi> who was allied to him by his wife deceaſed, he ſent his Secretary <hi>Mounſieur To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> who vſed all meanes poſſible to haue changed the Sentence of death into perpetual impriſonment, but many vrgent reaſons would not permit it, which they laboured to make the ſaid <hi>Mounſieur du Tonard,</hi> and the Lord <hi>D'eſdiguieres</hi> vnderſtand by ample and honourable Letters. We vnderſtood that the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Terrail</hi> was comming, accompanied with diuers of the Nobility of <hi>Dauphine</hi> to mediate the ſame; But <hi>Mounſieur du Tonard</hi> meeting them at <hi>Remilli,</hi> told them he was already diſpatched, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon they returned, ſending only to intreat his body, which was in like maner denyed for great reaſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing already buried in the Bullwarke, where the heads of thoſe were interred that were ſlaine at the <hi>Eſcala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da.</hi> He might haue made vſe of the grace they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him in the beginning, but he though that they could not conuince him, relying on the promiſes that the Bayliffe of <hi>Morges</hi> made him, that his man ſhould not be deliuered into their hands, as indeede he was ſtaid at the inſtance of that Bayliffe, till they made a ſecond voyage for him. After they had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:87:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> againſt him with that exact ſeuerity, hee had no more meanes to ſaue his life, or bend them with importunity.</p>
            <p>Solemne thankſgiuing was rendred for this deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance throughout all the Churches, the Sunday following being the 23. of Aprill. The <hi>Sauoyardes</hi> are much confounded; Some of <hi>Dauphyne,</hi> skou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring about <hi>Geneua,</hi> haue vſed great threates; but it is hoped, that when the King ſhall declare his will, it will ſtifle all theſe braues. There is good prouiſion had, againſt all future meanes of this enterpriſe, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping full Guardes vpon the firſt, and ſecond chaines; of them that ſearch all the Boates, which from hence forth ſhall come in ſingle, and halfe an hower one after the other, and the wood ſo piled, as one may goe in, and ſee all that is in the boate. In ſumme, it is hoped that this Mine is vtterly blowne vp. <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua</hi> hath recouered great courage; and got no leſſe reputation with the king, the Eſtates, and all the Churches of <hi>France,</hi> hauing made a notable eſſay of the ready, and entire affection of their Confederates the Lords of <hi>Berne.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:87:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
